<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Introduction to the U.S. Public Company Financial Information Repository</title>
        <author>
            <personname> </personname>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>The secxbrl.info Team</personname>
            <email>hello@secxbrl.info</email>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname> </personname>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>This document introduces both business users and technical engineers to the
                business-value adding features of the US Public Company Financial Information
                Repository, or SECXBRL.info for short, its architecture, and the various
                possibilities of how to access it. It is meant for users of the SECXBRL.info website
                who want to understand more about what is happening inside and as a starting point
                for users of the software interface and the software development platform,
                describing the general concepts, and from which to explore the more technical
                documentation.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>The <emphasis role="italic">US Public Company Financial Information
                Repository</emphasis>(SECXBRL.info) provides the ability to analyze the financial
            information of US public companies. US public companies are now required to submit
            reports, such as yearly (10-K) and quarterly financial reports (10-Q), to the US
            Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) using the globally standardized XBRL
            interactive data format. The SEC's purpose of this adoption is to carry <link
                xlink:href="http://www.sec.gov/spotlight/xbrl/what-oid-does.shtml"> "out the
                Commission's commitment to make financial disclosure accessible and easy to use
                through the application of interactive data."</link>. However, such data itself is
            not interactive, it only becomes valuable if it can be analyzed in a flexible, ad-hoc,
            real-time manner. The US Public Company Financial Information Repository SECXBRL.info,
            powered by 28.io, has been built to deliver on this promise. On the one hand, it is an
            out-of-the-box solution, complete with all the features needed from an analytical user
            interface to the real-time, simultaneous access to all the SEC 10-K and 10-Q filings
            since 2010. On the other hand, it is a fully customizable platform in which every
            component can be adapted to the specific requirements of a different data set or
            different analytical needs.</para>
        <para>The general approach was the following: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Preserve all the details of the original filing in order to provide a
                        complete audit trail of all presented figures.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add several layers of functionality in order to provide maximum
                        ease-of-use (highest layer), maximum flexibility (lowest layer), or a
                        well-balanced mix of the two (intermediate layer).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add domain-specific knowledge in order to help answer commonly asked
                        questions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Chose a system architecture that can deliver real-time performance.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Generalize the requirements such that private XBRL data can be analyzed
                        confidentially or that other repositories for public non-SEC data can be
                        built.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
          <title>Business-Value Adding Features</title>
	  	    <para>This section highlights some of the features of the SECXBRL.info service and platform
            that demonstrate how the business value that the XBRL community and the SEC had in mind
            can be reaped. These features address the requirements of sophisticated analytical
            capabilities, extensibility through further domain knowledge and data, and real-time
            ad-hoc performance.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Feature #1: Sophisticated Semantic Analytics</title>
            <para>The value of analyzing the SEC XBRL data does not come from finding out about an
                individual number. Or from extracting all the numbers from an individual filing. The
                most value comes from comparing reported figures of a single entity over time, from
                comparing the same figures across reporting entities, or from being able to look at
                a table of numbers exactly the way the company intended it to be. To realize these
                benefits requires a certain level of semantic analytical capability.</para>
            <para>Some of this sophisticated processing happens quietly in the background. The
                repository deals with situations like amended filings and the fact that information
                is duplicated in SEC filings. Filers typically report numbers not only for the
                current period but also for prior periods. The repository therefore has to determine
                which is the most up-to-date information for a given fiscal period. However, there
                is always a way to get to all the information using the 28.io development platform,
                for instance if someone wanted to find out if the numbers for one and the same
                fiscal period has been changed.</para>
            <para>Likewise, filers report figures for the same concept at various levels, e.g.
                business segments and consolidated entity. Most of the time, what is asked for is
                the information for the entity of focus of the public company filing, that means the
                consolidated entity. Again, this is automatically taken care of by way of how the
                data is represented and the semantic analytical intelligence that is applied to
                it.</para>
            <para>Another important issue when querying SEC XBRL financial filings is that public
                companies can use many different US GAAP XBRL taxonomy concepts to label reported
                information. This does make sense for an individual company but makes it impossible
                to compare figures across entities. In order to deal with this situation, the
                capability of establishing semantic mappings was built in such a way that these can
                be applied for these kinds of analyses. If you consider that SEC XBRL financial
                filers use more than 45 different concepts to report “Revenues” you begin see the
                benefits of a built-in mapping. One such synonyms mapping that is available for
                everyone using the repository are the 51 Fundamental Accounting Concepts (see <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.secxbrl.info/concept-map/FundamentalAccountingConcepts"
                    >http://www.secxbrl.info/concept-map/FundamentalAccountingConcepts</link>).</para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Example #1 - R&amp;D Expenses</title>
                <para>For example, these are the concepts used within SEC XBRL financial filings to
                    report on R&amp;D expenses, and that have been mapped to the Fundamental
                    Accounting Concept fac:ResearchAndDevelopment:</para>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>us-gaap:ResearchAndDevelopmentExpense</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>us-gaap:ResearchAndDevelopmentExpenseExcludingAcquiredInProcessCost</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>us-gaap:ResearchAndDevelopmentExpenseSoftwareExcludingAcquiredInProcessCost
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>us-gaap:ResearchAndDevelopmentInProcess</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>us-gaap:ResearchAndDevelopmentAssetAcquiredOtherThanThroughBusinessCombinationWrittenOff</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
                <para>Using the semantic mapping for fac:ResearchAndDevelopment, one is now able to
                    retrieve all figures representing R&amp;D expense for all DOW30 entities for the
                    fiscal period FY and the fiscal year 2012. Retrieve the results as XML.</para>
                <para>This is how the result looks like in the SECXBRL.info website (see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.secxbrl.info/example/ResearchAndDevelopment"
                        >http://www.secxbrl.info/example/ResearchAndDevelopment</link>): </para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image09.jpg" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
                <para>The data for every analysis that can be performed on the SECXBRL.info website
                    is also accessible through a web service API. In fact, the SECXBRL.info website
                    uses exactly this API to retrieve the data from the repository. For this
                    example, the API call would be </para>
                <para>http://secxbrl.xbrl.io/v1/_queries/public/api/facts.jq?_method=POST&amp;format=xml&amp;</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>concept=fac:ResearchAndDevelopment&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>map=FundamentalAccountingConcepts&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalPeriod=FY&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalPeriod=FY&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalYear=2012&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>tag=dow30</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>This query is more generic than the website as it additionally allows to
                    simultaneously select multiple concepts, multiple entities, and even multiple
                    fiscal periods and fiscal years. Furthermore, the facts retrieved by this query
                    can be explicitly filtered by any dimension that is included in the
                    repository.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Example #2 - Fact Table for Balance Sheet</title>
                <para>The XBRL filing, however, does not only contain individual facts, but also
                    complete financial statements like balance sheets, income statements, cash flow
                    statements, significant accounting policies, long-term debt maturities,
                    subsequent events, and so on, so-called components. There are three parts to a
                    financial statement: (1) its fact table, (2) its model structure, and (3) its
                    visual rendering. The fact table contains the individual facts. The model
                    structure puts these facts into dimensions and hierarchies. The visual rendering
                    describes how the statement looks like when printed in a report. Right now,
                    SECXBRL.info does not provide renderings of these statements, but it is thought
                    that this will be added in the future.</para>
                <para>This is how the fact table of Coca Cola’s 10-K balance sheet of 2013 looks
                    like in the SECXBRL.info website (see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.secxbrl.info/facttable/bf334638-7cc2-4ef0-b514-65bee4bef510"
                        >http://www.secxbrl.info/facttable/bf334638-7cc2-4ef0-b514-65bee4bef510</link>): </para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image10.jpg" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
                <para>The API call for this example would be </para>
                <para>http://secxbrl.xbrl.io/v1/_queries/public/api/facttable-for-component.jq?_method=POST&amp;format=xml&amp;</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ticker=ko&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalYear=2013&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalPeriod=FY&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>disclosure=BalanceSheet</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Example #3 - Model Structure for Balance Sheet</title>
                <para>Similarly, this is how the model structure of Coca Cola’s 10-K balance sheet
                    of 2013 looks like in the SECXBRL.info website (see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.secxbrl.info/modelstructure/bf334638-7cc2-4ef0-b514-65bee4bef510"
                        >http://www.secxbrl.info/modelstructure/bf334638-7cc2-4ef0-b514-65bee4bef510</link>).</para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image11.jpg" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
                <para>The API call for this example would be</para>
                <para>http://secxbrl.xbrl.io/v1/_queries/public/api/modestructure-for-component.jq?_method=POST&amp;format=xml&amp;</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ticker=ko&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalYear=2013&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalPeriod=FY&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>disclosure=BalanceSheet</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
    		</sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Feature #2: Custom Reports</title>
            <para>The aim of SECXBRL.info is to provide functionality that goes above and beyond
                merely accessing the information that is contained in the filings. The filings
                provide a view of the business situation of a company in the way the management of
                this company wants to portray it. Analysts, on the other hand, want to be able to
                define a view of the same business situation in a way that corresponds with how they
                evaluate companies. It is therefore important for the usefulness of such an
                analytics platform to allow for the definition of custom reports.</para>
            <para>Such requirement would most likely consist of (i) accessing information from
                across multiple fact tables and (ii) combining this information into one report. One
                example of such a report are the Fundamental Accounting Concepts (see <link
                    xlink:href="http://fundamentalaccountingconcepts.wikispaces.com/">
                    http://fundamentalaccountingconcepts.wikispaces.com/</link>). Because this
                report is considered so fundamental, it has already been implemented in
                SECXBRL.info.</para>
            <para>In order to define such a report, one would have to consider:</para>
            <para><itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Map facts:</emphasis> Understand which US GAAP
                            and XBRL extension concepts the filer has used in order to report the
                            relevant facts. This inquiry can be performed by retrieving the fact
                            tables (see Example #2 - Fact Table for Balance Sheet) and model
                            structures (see Example #3 - Model Structure for Balance Sheet) from the
                            filings.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Impute facts:</emphasis> If a fact is not
                            reported, define the formula to impute the value of the required fact
                            based on the values of other facts that were included in the
                            filing.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Validate facts:</emphasis> Create rules (e.g.
                            formulas that need to produce a certain result) that help to assess the
                            quality and consistency of the facts that are to be included in the
                            custom report.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>The approach for defining a custom report consists of three
                steps:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Identify the concepts:</emphasis> Specify the
                            concepts that are to be included in the report. This specification needs
                            to be in the XBRL Infoset format. This website contains the
                            specification of the Fundamental Accounting Concepts, which can be used
                            as an example: <link xlink:href="http://www.xbrlsite.com/2013/fac/"
                                >http://www.xbrlsite.com/2013/fac/</link>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Map the concepts:</emphasis> Provide a mapping
                            file between the requested concepts and the US GAAP XBRL Taxonomy
                            concepts filers have used. An example of such a mapping for
                            fac:ResearchAndDevelopment was already given in the section Example #1 -
                            R&amp;D Expense. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Specify the rules to impute non-reported
                                facts:</emphasis> Third, the business rules between the concepts
                            need to be specified. Again, a standard format is available which
                            articulates these relations, XBRL Formula: <link
                                xlink:href="http://www.xbrlsite.com/2013/fac/FundamentalAccountingConcepts_Formulas.xml"
                                >
                                http://www.xbrlsite.com/2013/fac/FundamentalAccountingConcepts_Formulas.xml</link>.
                            Currently, SECXBRL.info does not support XBRL Formulas, but it is
                            thought that this will be added in the future.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Example #4 - Fundamental Accounting Concepts Report</title>
                <para>As mentioned, one such custom report is included in SECXBRL.info: Fundamental
                    Accounting Concepts.</para>
                <para>This is how the part on the cash flow statement of the Fundamental Accounting
                    Concepts report for Coca Cola’s 2013 10-K filing looks like in the SECXBRL.info
                    website (see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.secxbrl.info/information/0000021344/2013/FY"
                        >http://www.secxbrl.info/information/0000021344/2013/FY</link>).</para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image12.jpg" scale="60"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
                <para>This API call returns the fact table for the report named
                    FundamentalAccountingConcepts for Coca Cola’s 2013 10-K: </para>
                <para>http://secxbrl.xbrl.io/v1/_queries/public/api/facttable-for-report.jq?_method=POST&amp;format=xml&amp;</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>report=FundamentalAccountingConcepts&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ticker=ko&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalYear=2012&amp;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>fiscalPeriod=FY</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Feature #3: Real-Time</title>
            <para>Most analyses are ad-hoc and therefore have to be interactive. The answer of one
                question leads to another question. The goal of SECXBRL.info, hence, was to provide
                a real-time analytics platform. While it is relatively easy to bring back an
                individual fact in real-time, the proof of performance would be an analysis that
                would require data from all the filings in the repository. </para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Example #5 - Assets and Liabilites &amp; Equity Across the Whole
                    Repository</title>
				        <para>The first such example is to compute the sum of all values reported against the
                    concept ‘us-gaap:Assets’ across all 10-K SEC XBRL financial filings aggregated
                    by fiscal period.</para>
                <para>This is how the result looks like in the SECXBRL.info website (see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.secxbrl.info/example/TotalAssets"
                        >http://www.secxbrl.info/example/TotalAssets</link>): </para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image13.jpg" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
                <para>The second such example is to compute the sum of all values reported against
                    the concept ‘fac:LiabilitiesAndEquity’ across all 10-K SEC XBRL financial
                    filings aggregated by fiscal period. This example is more computationally
                    intensive because it includes a mapping from the reported concepts to the
                    fundamental accounting concepts.</para>
                <para>This is how the result looks like in the SECXBRL.info website (see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.secxbrl.info/example/TotalLiabilitiesAndEquity"
                        >http://www.secxbrl.info/example/TotalLiabilitiesAndEquity</link>): </para>
                <para><inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/image14.jpg" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject></para>
				        <para>This query takes 4.6 seconds to execute, which is absolutely acceptable for such
                    an analysis. The reasons for this exceptional performance lie in the choice of
                    the underlying technology: from the 28.io unified information access platform to
                    the MongoDB NoSQL data store.</para>
            </sect3>
		    </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Feature #4: Bring Your Own Filings</title>
            <para>SECXBRL.info builds upon the 28.io platform and the generic semantic business
                reporting architecture and customizes it by (1) populating the XBRL data store with
                the SEC 10-K and 10-Q filings and (2) defining an SEC profile. It was specifically
                designed with extensibility in mind. This extensibility can go into two directions:
                (1) to include user-specific non-public filings and (2) to be used for non-SEC data
                sets. Users will be able to bring their own filings using the SEC profile, which
                will be visible only to them and which they can then analyze by themselves or
                compare with the public filing data set. It is also possible to create a whole new
                XBRL profile by replacing the SEC specific configuration with another XBRL-compliant
                one, i.e. FDIC, IFRS, FinRep, CoRep, or Environmental, Social and Governance (ESG)
                reporting. The effort to develop a new XBRL profile is small compared to all the
                functionality that has already been put in place to implement a generic XBRL
                analytics platform.</para>
		    </sect2>
	  </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Two Ways to Use the Repository - and Any Way in Between</title>
        <para>The SECXBRL.info US Public Company Financial Information Repository has been built as
            a specific implementation of a more generic business reporting platform.</para>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/image08.jpg" scale="75"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>This leads to the two extreme opposite ways of using the repository: (1) take
            everything out of the box, without any specific customization, or (2) use the generic
            platform and build your own repository. Since the platform is fully flexible, the
            SECXBRL.info service can be used as a starting point for custom usage for which every
            component can be extended or completely replaced, this leads to a virtually unlimited
            number of ways of how to use the repository.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>SECXBRL.info Service</title>
            <para>The SECXBRL.info service is an out-of-the-box offering, complete with all the
                necessary components from a data analytics website <link
                    xlink:href="http://secxbrl.info/">http://secxbrl.info/</link>, a web
                service-based API (a full documentation can be found here: <link
                    xlink:href="http://secxbrl.info/api">http://secxbrl.info/api</link>), a
                pre-defined report for the most commonly used fundamental accounting concepts, a
                specific SEC data profile, and all the SEC 10-K and 10-Q filings since 2010. More
                details about the Fundamental Accounting Concepts report and the SEC profile can be
                found on the SECXBRL.info support website (see <link
                    xlink:href="https://secxbrl.zendesk.com/"
                >https://secxbrl.zendesk.com/</link>).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Custom Business Reporting Solution</title>
            <para>Everything in the SECXBRL.info service can be replace, extended, or taken as a
                starting point for creating a custom solution. The custom app implements the user
                interface as a mobile, client-based or web-based application. The API can be built
                to the requirements of the front-end application or any other information consumer.
                There are plenty of ways to add domain or application specific knowledge through
                rules, mappings, and reports. Great care was used to separate out any SEC-specific
                functionality into an SEC profile. This allows to easily switch the SEC profile with
                any other XBRL-based profile. Finally, other XBRL-formatted data can be loaded into
                the data store and accessed through the XBRL connector, or other private data can be
                joined through any of the many other 28.io connectors.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>
